Okay, good. All right, so today's דף daf is י"ז. yud-zayin. We
start on the bottom of ט"ז עמוד ב' tes-zayin amud-bet
and we're having this whole issue about being essentially what I'll call
a sharecropper of sheep for a flock of a non-Jew, like this
week's פרשה. parsha. And the fact that the non-Jew has rights in
the principal and then in the children if he needs to make
up the principal means that they're exempt from the first-born, at least
the first generation. Let's take a look at the
משנה. Mishnah. העמיד ולדותיהם תחת אמותיהם—the He-emid v'ladoteihem tachat imoteihem two dots
on ט"ז עמוד ב' tes-zayin amud-bet about 10, 12 lines from the
bottom—העמיד ולדותיהם תחת אמותיהם ולדי ולדות פטורין. He-emid v'ladoteihem tachat imoteihem v'ladei
v'ladot paturin. So if you designated the children in the place of
the mothers—תוספות Tosafot says it means that the mother's original flock actually
died and you had a substitute, or as רש"י Rashi says, it
just means that you specifically said to the non-Jew, 'Here, you can
use the children to make up the difference'—then it gives the children
primary status as if the non-Jew owns them and then gives him
rights in the children's children. So it all goes down another generation.
So the children's children, the grandchildren of the original flock are exempt
as future mothers and you would need to be the great-grandchildren to
be obligated. At that point, he has no more rights.
אמר רב הונא ולדות
פטורין ולדי ולדותיהן חייבין. Amar Rav Huna: v'ladot paturin, v'ladei v'ladoteihem chayavin.
So he said the simple read of the משנה, Mishnah, which is
that the children are exempt, the grandchildren are obligated. We're going basically
back to the first part of the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, let me
just see. No, that's if העמיד ולדותיהם תחת אמותיהם. He-emid v'ladoteihem tachat
imoteihem. We're going back. That was just a line from the משנה.
Mishnah. But we're just going back to the, what do you call
it, the סתם משנה. stam mishnah. Right, exactly, to the simple case.
רב יהודה אמר ולדי ולדו
נמי פטורין. Rav Yehuda amar: v'ladei v'lado nami paturin. Even in a
normal case, the grandchildren are exempt. Again, and when we say exempt,
we mean exempt as mothers, so their children would not be בכור.
bechor. ולדי ולדי ולדו חייבין—the v'ladei v'ladei v'lado chayavin great-grandchildren are obligated.
Okay, so basically on the first line in the משנה, Mishnah, רב
הונא Rav Huna reads the משנה Mishnah like its simple sense that
only the first generation is exempt,
and רב יהודה Rav Yehuda reads it that two generations are exempt.
תנן, Tnan, and now this is why we quote, we have this
discussion on this line because we're going to focus on the next
case.
תנן העמיד ולדות תחת אמותיהם—when Tnan: He-emid v'ladot tachat imoteihem you set
the children to take stead of the mother—then ולדי ולדות פטורין, v'ladei
v'ladot paturin, the grandchildren are exempt. So when are the grandchildren exempt?
Only when you specifically made the children to substitute for the mother.
טעמא דהעמיד—it's Ta'ama de-he-emid only if you designated the children to substitute
for the mother. הא לא העמיד—without Ha lo he-emid that special case—לא,
lo, it would not be true. It would only be the children
that are exempt, not the grandchildren. תיובתא דרב יהודה—that's Tyuvta de-Rav Yehuda
a contradiction to רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. אמר לך רב יהודה—רב יהודה
would say back to you: הוא הדין אף על גב דלא העמיד.
Hu hadin af al gav de-lo he-emid. Even without that special case,
it would go down to the grandchildren. והא קמשמע לן—so Ve-ha kamashma
lan why did it say if you designated the children it goes
to the grandchildren? To tell
you: אפילו העמיד נמי דאורחיה דעובדי כוכבים למתפס בנא הוי כמי דלא
העמיד
ולדי ולדו פטורין ולדי ולדי ולדות חייבין. afilu he-emid nami de-orchei de-ovdei
kochavim lemitpas b'na, havei ke-mi de-lo he-emid, v'ladei v'lado paturin, v'ladei v'ladei
v'ladot chayavin. Okay, so what is the reason it says that? To
tell you, one minute, let me just check across a minute.
One minute. Right. Okay, so it's right, because it's telling you that
I might have thought—remember רב יהודה Rav Yehuda now is the one
that's arguing that the non-Jew has more rights to seize the flock.
He assumes that he can seize the flock up to the grandchildren.
So he's saying, given that I in general think that—of course, part
of the question might be here just to ask like what are
they really debating, nobody's actually talking about הלכה halacha here. Why don't
they discuss, well, how much are your rights? Like the other day,
is that a normal הלכה? halacha? It seems to be that the
point here is that whatever there were sort of common practices about
how this worked. And maybe the question here was, yeah, maybe under
some times the non-Jew would seize the
great-great-grandchildren, sometimes only the children, and maybe part of the question is
like what was he actually entitled to by law, maybe not even
by הלכה halacha law, but by the law that was the civil
law that was guiding their cases. So anyway, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
basically reads, I should say re-reads the משנה Mishnah to say that
the non-Jew's primary right is not only limited to the children, it
goes to the grandchildren. So he's saying, given that I'm already looking
and seeing that the non-Jew has more rights and maybe acknowledging sometimes
when the non-Jew grabs second generation and so on, maybe you might
think that the non-Jew's rights go to infinite
generations and therefore it doesn't have any end because I'm already willing
to recognize it to the second generation. So therefore he makes the
point, that's why the משנה Mishnah says no, even in a case
of העמיד, he-emid, it stops at the second generation. Without העמיד, he-emid,
it's also second generation, but even with העמיד, he-emid, it stops at
the second generation and don't think that it keeps on going between
העמיד he-emid and בין לא העמיד. bein lo he-emid.
I know, it's a difficult read. So let's
read. I know, it's a very difficult read. Don't worry, the גמרא's
Gemara going to reject it. It's a very difficult read. Okay, so
he says like this: So אמר לך רב ביבי, Amar lecha Rav
Bibi, let's read that again, הוא הדין אף על גב דלא המיד,
hu hadin af al gav delo hemid, even without the special case,
he has up to two generations. והא קמשמע לן, Ve-hachmashmalan, so why
did they say with המיד hemid he has two generations? אפילו המיד
נמי, Afilu hemid nami,
even in the case of המיד, hemid, I might have said דאורחי
דעכו"ם למתפס בנא de-orchi d'akum l'mitpas b'na and
that since a non-Jew generally goes one generation further than maybe he
normally is entitled, and maybe he keeps on going infinite generations way
רש"י Rashi says it, so הוי כמי, havei k'mi,
nevertheless you might think that with המיד hemid you go up to
three generations or four generations, no, even with המיד, hemid, הוי כמו
דלא המיד, havei k'mo delo hemid, it's not different than the case
of לא המיד. lo hemid. ולדי ולדות פטור ולדי ולדי ולדות חייבין.
Vladei vlados patur vladei vladei vlados chayavin. It's two generations are exempt,
three are obligated. So basically he's saying as Michael succinctly put it,
there's no difference המיד hemid and not המיד. hemid. It's telling you
even with המיד, hemid, it's limited to two generations. But the real
point is it always is two generations. Okay, but that's definitely a
re-read of the משנה. Mishnah. Let's take a look. תנן. Tnan. So
we're going to try again. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer, the end of the משנה Mishnah says, רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says אפילו עד עשרה דורות פטורין,
afilu ad asara doros pturin, even until ten generations. He's the one
that clearly says ad infinitum. שחריותו לאו בכוחן Shachriyuso lo b'kochan and
the non-Jew can always seize, you know, future generations to make up
the difference. בשלמא לרב יהודה, Bishlama l'Rav Yehuda, now we're going to
say that that maybe even suggests for רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda Why?
דאמר נחית תנא קמא לדרי d'amar nachis tanna kamma l'darei that the
תנא קמא tanna kamma says, you know, that you can even go
until second generation. So therefore היינו דאמר ליה רבן שמעון בן גמליאל,
hainu d'amar lei Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, top of י"ז עמוד א',
yud zayin amud aleph, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
comes and responds אפילו עד עשרה דורות פטורין afilu ad asara doros
pturin
that he says that it's not, you know, not only two generations,
it goes infinite generations. אלא לרב הונא Ela l'Rav Huna דאמר לא
נחית תנא קמא לדרי d'amar lo nachis tanna kamma l'darei but according
to רב הונא Rav Huna
that we never even went beyond the children, we're not even talking
about how many generations. Right, if I say, if I'm going beyond
the children, then I'm counting numbers of generations. I'm saying up to
two generations you're exempt. So רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel is going to say infinite generations you're exempt. But according to
the other approach, I'm not saying generations, I'm just saying the kids
are exempt. So according to that, then why
מאי אפילו עד עשרה דורות? mai afilu ad asara doros? Why do
you say even until ten generations? Now it's a funny question because
maybe even asks, maybe that's his position of עשרה דורות. asara doros.
Yeah, so let me just, let me just see, check רש"י Rashi
again. So רש"י Rashi so says, hold on,
right, meaning why not just say, no, even like the third generation?
Which is a funny question, you know, but the point is like
this: if I, if, if the first position says two generations, so
obviously two generations, then there's a lot of other possibilities, three, four,
five, six, seven, and you need רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel to say infinite generations. But if the first one just
says children, basically denies the whole idea of generations, then if I
just say, no, no, no, it goes even into the generations, it
goes even into the second and the third generation, so then it
somehow should be assumed that it doesn't matter how many. It's a
funny, no, that's how
he can go on both, both paths.
I, I understand. עשרה דורות Asara doros is just more explicit. Somehow
the גמרא Gemara assumes that if the first position had just said
children, then it would be sufficient for the second position to say,
no, it goes even into the generations. And once I say it
goes into the generations, it's meant no particular reason to draw a
line in any particular place. But if the first position is admitting
it goes into the generations and drawing a line between two and
three, then you need a next position to say there's ad, you
know, עד עשרה, ad asara, there's no limit. Okay, so that's a
more of a, whatever, you know, more of a phrasing question and
it's not, I think it's hard for us to understand why it's
such a strong question because it's clearer to say עשרה דורות. asara
doros. Anyway, let's take a look at the גמרא's Gemara answer. אמר
לך רב הונא, Amar lecha Rav Huna, רב הונא Rav Huna says
back, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אהמיד קאי. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel a-hemid
ka. So here it's sort of saying it that he, he grants
the case. You're right. If we had not introduced the concept of
generations, he would not have had to say ten, but we did
introduce the concept of generations. Where? In the case where you made
the children substitute for their mother. In that case, even the תנא
קמא tanna kamma does say you go up to two generations. דנחית
לדרי, de-nachis l'darei, and in that case we do go to two
generations when the children take the place of the mother. And therefore
since there we are saying two generations, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel can't just say it goes into the generations, he
has to say it goes infinite, עד עשרה דורות. ad asara doros.
Okay, so תא שמע, ta shema, let's try it again. המקבל צאן
ברזל מן העכו"ם, Ha-mekabel tzon barzel min ha-akum, ולדות פטורין ולדי ולדות
לא. vlados pturin vladei vlados lo. So it says, the ברייתא braita
says that if you, if you receive the sheep from the non-Jew,
ולדות vlados are exempt, and the ולדי ולדות, vladei vlados, now it's
a little unclear where this ברייתא braita ended. Did it just say
ולדות פטורין vlados pturin end, or did it say ולדות פטורין ולדי
ולדות לא? vlados pturin vladei vlados lo? That's a funny phrase of
a ברייתא. braita. If it was really the right way it would
have said ולדי ולדות חייבין. vladei vlados chayavin. But it might have
been the גמרא's Gemara read of the ברייתא. braita. But anyway, it
says the children are exempt, so either presumably or it's explicitly or
implicitly saying the grandchildren are obligated. So here it's very clear, only
the children, not the grandchildren. תיובתא דרב יהודה, tiyuvta d'Rav Yehuda,
that's a contradiction to רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. אמר לך רב יהודה,
Amar lach Rav Yehuda אימא הן וולדותיהן. eima hen u-vladoseihen. When it
says, when it says that the ולדות vlados are exempt, don't read
it just the children. children, it means they and their children, the
they, the implicit they being the children. So the children and their
children are exempt. So when it says children, it doesn't mean children,
it means the children's children. Okay, so the Gemara says איכא דאמרי,
ika d'amri, some say that that's what we assumed it meant. הן
וולדותיהן פטור, hein uvladoteihen patur, or that was the text, that says
they and their children are exempt, which means the children and the
children's children. תיובתא דרב הונא, tiyuvta d'Rav Huna, contradiction Rav Huna. אמר
לך רב הונא, amar lach Rav Huna, Rav Huna would say back
to you, no, אימא הן וולדות פטור, eima hein uvladot patur, they
the children are exempt, וולדי וולדות חייב, vladtei vladot chayav, the grandchildren
are obligated. So the Gemara ends without being resolved, although there's no
question that Rav Huna is the easier read of the Mishnah, that
basically in a normal case the children are exempt, in a special
case where the children substitute for the mothers, then it goes one
generation further and the grandchildren are exempt. Anyway, everybody agrees to the
principle that until the generation that the non-Jew has a right to
cease to make up for the principal, that generation is exempt even
as mothers. Okay, not just as children, but as mothers, as future
mothers. Now we thankfully put that aside and move on to the
next case. I mean it was... and we look at the issue
here of
which is revisiting an old case about when the child does not
look like the mother. Okay, so it said רחל שילדה מין עז,
rachel sheyalda min ez, if a sheep gives birth to a goat
or a goat to a sheep, or it looks like a goat,
looks like a sheep, you're exempt from בכור. bechor. אתא רב הושעיא
מנהרדעא, ata Rav Hoshaya mi'Nehardea, Rav Hoshaya from Nehardea came, ואייתי מתניתא
בידיה, v'ayti matnita bideih,
and he had a Baraita in his hands, and here was his
Baraita. רחל בת עז ועז בת רחל, rachel bat ez v'ez bat
rachel, this case, a sheep the son of a goat or a
goat the son of a sheep, a daughter rather, רבי מאיר מחייב
וחכמים
פוטרין. Rabbi Meir mechayev v'chachamim potrin. Rabbi Meir says it's obligated and
the Chachamim say it's exempt. So basically it's our Mishnah's case, except
here you have a Rabbi Meir that says חייב. chayav. So we're
going to try to figure out the Rabbi Meir. So אמר ליה
רב הושעיא לרבה, amar leih Rav Hoshaya l'Rabba, so Rav Hoshaya said
to Rabba, this is not Rav Oshaya who had the Baraita, it's
Rav Hoshaya said to
Rabba. כי אזלת לקמיה דרב הונא, ki azlat l'kamei d'Rav Huna, when
you go in front of Rav Huna, is Rav Huna from Nehardea?
I think he is. I'm...
anybody know that? I'm not good at that. Okay, we had Charlie
here who would tell us in a minute on his whatever. Anyway,
I think so because this anyway this was a teaching that came
from Nehardea. So Rav Hoshaya said to Rabba, when you go to
Rav Huna, בעי מיניה, bei mineih,
ask him the following question. רבי מאיר מחייב למאי, Rabbi Meir mechayev
l'mai, when Rabbi Meir says you're חייב chayav when the child doesn't
look like the mother, what's the halacha? What's, you know, what category
of halacha are we talking about? אילימא לבכורה, eileima l'bechora,
because it was just a Baraita, it didn't have any particular context.
It just said, oh, if the mother is the goat and the
father is the sheep or vice versa, I'm sorry, the mother is
the sheep and the child is a goat or vice versa, Rabbi
Meir says חייב. chayav. What halacha? So you know there are a
lot of different cases that we could be talking about. So if
we're talking about בכור, bechor, אילימא לבכורה, eileima l'bechora, ולית ליה לרבי
מאיר אך בכור שור, v'leit leih l'Rabbi Meir ach bechor shor, right?
We said this Baraita, we said this teaching before. However, the firstborn
of an ox, עד דהוא שור ובכורו שור, ad d'hu shor u'bechoro
shor,
it has to look like its... the mother has to be an
ox, a cow, and the child has to be a cow, it
has to look like the mother. Now it's funny that the Gemara
takes it for granted that nobody could argue on that position, but
it does. It says, ah, don't we know that the mother has
to look like the child for
בכור? bechor? אלא לראשית הגז, ela l'reishit hagez, okay, go back to
last Masechet, the shearing of the wool. ולית ליה הא דתני דבי
רבי ישמעאל, v'leit leih ha d'tani d'bei Rabbi Yishmael, כבשים שצמרן קשה
פטורים מראשית הגז, kvassim she'tzamran kasheh pturim me'reishit hagez,
if you have sheep that has hard wool, you don't... you're exempt
from ראשית הגז, reishit hagez, שנאמר ומגז כבשי יתחמם, shene'emar u'migez kvassai
yitchamam,
from the shearing of my sheep he will be warmed. So if
the wool is hard and it doesn't... not like soft and doesn't
like heat, you know, sort of fit to the contours of the
body or whatever, it's not... you're not חייב. chayav. And if here
you have a goat the son of a sheep, so clearly it's
going to be goat's hair and or like goat's hair and it
will... it should be exempt, so just for a side reason, not
because of נדמה nidmeh but because of the quality of the wool.
So אמר ליה, amar leih, so rather than asking Rav Huna, here's
what Rabba said back to Rav Hoshaya. נחזי אנן, nechzei anan, let's
figure it out ourselves. Okay, it's like נחזי אנן nechzei anan is
like, let's... let's not bother asking Rav Huna, let's try to figure
it out ourselves. נחזי אנן, nechzei anan, let's take a look. הכא
במאי עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan, what are we talking about? ברחל שילדה
מין עז, b'rachel sheyalda min ez, here's a good way to say
the case. It would be a sheep that was born of a
goat, okay, or you know, I'm sorry, I said it wrong, a
sheep that gave birth to something that looked like a goat, ואביו
תייש, v'aviv tayish, and this was a mixed marriage because the father
was a goat as well. So basically here's the case, right? Very
often we talk about נדמה nidmeh and we bracket the question of
who the father is. Meaning just the fact that it looks different
is enough of a basis for exemption. But we could also ask
the question about is it a mixed... is it a, you know,
is it a mixed breed? And that's different from just the נדמה
nidmeh case, that's a כלאים kilayim case when it's a mixed breed.
So he wants to make it different if it looks like it's
a mixed breed? Well, let's take a look. So he says maybe
this is the case, נחזי אנן, nechzei anan, exactly. That he said
this is the case. Mother is a sheep, father is a goat,
you get... I don't think this is even possible, but whatever, and
the child looks like a goat. So what's the issue? It's even
less like the mother, so why should it be חייב? chayav? So
let's take a look. So the Gemara says וחוששין לזרע האב לענין
אותו ואת בנו.
v'choshishin l'zera ha'av l'inyan
oto v'et bno.
Well let's take a look.
So he says maybe this is the case. Maybe not. Exactly. He
says this is the case. Mother is a sheep, father is a
goat. Again, I don't think this is even possible, but whatever, and
the child looks like a goat. So what's the issue? It's even
less like the
mother, so why should it be חייב? chayev? So let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara says, ובחוששים לזרע האב לעניין אותו ואת
בנו קמיפלגי. ubechosshim lezer ha'av le'inyan oso ve'es bno kemiplagi. The question
is for the הלכה halacha for אותו ואת בנו oso ve'es bno
does the father matter? Not for the question about ראשית הגז reishis
hageiz because the wool is still an issue. Not for the issue
of בכורה, bechora, which obviously the focus is totally on the mother,
פטר רחם, petter rechem, but on אותו ואת בנו, oso ve'es bno,
which if you'll remember ironically the Torah says אותו oso in the
masculine, but we interpret it to be the mother because the father
because the question is חוששים לזרע האב. choshshim lezera ha'av. Now חוששים
לזרע האב choshshim lezera ha'av doesn't mean do we know who the
father is, it means does it matter who the father is. In
the animal world in the animal world you know does the fact
that he's just the sperm donor, that he's the biological father if
there's no sense of family, does that create any identity in any
sense of relationship within the animal world. That's the question of חוששים
לזרע האב. choshshim lezera ha'av. Okay, so here's the debate. וחוששים לזרע
האב לעניין אותו ואת בנו קמיפלגי. vechoshshim lezera ha'av le'inyan oso ve'es
bno kemiplagi. That's the debate. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir סבר savar חוששים
לזרע האב. choshshim lezera ha'av. You are concerned with the father. So
since the father is a goat and here's why we'd say that
the child looks like a goat, because maybe if the father was
a goat and the child looked like a sheep there would be
you'd say they're not related at all, meaning not that he's not
the biological father but that you can't define it as a connection.
But in this case where the father's a goat and the child
actually looks more like the father than it does like the mother,
maybe here you'd you know it's even a stronger reason to say
it should be an issue of אותו ואת בנו. oso ve'es bno.
So that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. ורבנן veRabbanan סברי savri
and the Rabbis hold אין חוששים לזרע האב. ein choshshim lezera ha'av.
No, even in that case the father's irrelevant and even though the
child looks like a goat and the mother's a sheep there's no
אותו ואת בנו oso ve'es bno with the father. Okay, but wasn't
the actual when we had that debate of חוששים לזרע האב, choshshim
lezera ha'av, weren't the two people חנניה Chananya ורבנן? veRabbanan? No. So
that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to say. Now that debate would
be even if everybody's a sheep, meaning the father's a sheep, the
mother's a sheep and the child is a sheep, still the question
is does the father matter. But here we're maybe making it like
a special case within that,
but there's even more of a reason to connect the child to
the father because the child's a goat and the father's a goat.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי ei hachi if
that's their debate, ליפלגו בחוששים לזרע האב בעלמא בפלוגתא דחנניה ורבנן. liflego
bechoshshim lezera ha'av be'alma beplugta deChananya veRabbanan. Like Michael says, so why
do they actually have a special case of נדמה? nidme? Put it
in the context of the larger debate of are you חייב chayev
for the father by אותו ואת בנו. oso ve'es bno. Okay, so
it doesn't sound like that's what they're arguing about. אלא לעולם לבכורה.
ela le'olam lebechora. We're really it's about בכורה bechora like what our
משנה's mishna talking about. But now we have the problem, how could
anybody say you're חייב chayev in בכורה bechora when the child doesn't
look like the mother? So forget about the father, it's בכורה, bechora,
we're ignoring the father. And by the way, you realize that, right?
Even if it's the father's third or fourth or hundredth child, בכורה
bechora always goes by the mother for for פדיון הבן pidyon haben
as well for humans, it all goes by the mother. So forget
about that. We're not even by בכורה bechora we're completely ignoring the
father. Okay, so then what's the issue? The child doesn't look like
the mother. How could anybody say you're חייב? chayev? והכא במאי עסקינן
vehacha bemai askinan what are we talking about? ברחל בת רחל בת
עז. berachel bas rachel bas ez. So it is a sheep the
daughter of a sheep or actually it should be the son. Okay,
בת עז bas ez and the
mother was the daughter of a goat. Okay, so yes, the child
looks like the mother, but the mother itself didn't look like its
mother. So basically the
question is like this. How do you understand the הלכה halacha that
נדמה nidme is exempt? Is the הלכה halacha that the child has
to look like the mother? So that happened here. The sheep looked
like its mother sheep. Or is the idea that once an animal
comes out not looking like its mother, it gets labeled a נדמה
nidme and נדמה nidme like puts it in a different category. And
if that's true, no matter how many generations after, once the mother's
a נדמה, nidme, all the children of a נדמה nidme are also
a נדמה. nidme. That's the question. Okay, so
so let's take a look. ברחל בת רחל בת עז. berachel bas
rachel bas ez. The grandmother that the grandmother's the goat. No, no.
The
grandmother's a goat,
the mother's a sheep, the daughter's a sheep. Okay. So the daughter
the daughter the son because we're talking about
בכור. bechor. So if you say the הלכה halacha of נדמה nidme
is just a דין din that for בכורה bechora the child has
to look like the mother, sheep sheep, it works. Okay. This is
like that game they play with kids, Set, you know how anyway,
but if the הלכה halacha is that when you have when it
goes when it changes sort of appearance, it gets called a new
category of נדמה, nidme, then the
grandchild is the child of a נדמה nidme and is exempt. So
that's the question. Okay, so let's take a look. מר סבר mar
savar one holds זיל בתר אימיה zil basar ime just look at
the mother והאי לאו נדמה הוא, vehai lav nidme hu, the mother
this isn't a נדמה nidme because the child looks like the mother.
ומר סבר umar savar and the other holds זיל בתר אימיה דאימיה,
zil basar ime de'ime, no, you gotta go back to the grandmother
והאי נדמה הוא. vehai nidme hu. So this grandchild is the child
of a נדמה nidme which makes it a נדמה nidme as well.
So even if it was let's say a goat let's say it
instead of goat sheep sheep, it would be goat sheep goat.
Oh, excellent. So that's the other possibility. ואי בעית אימא ve'ee ba'is
eima if you want, so that's one question, which is a great
question. What’s נדמה?
nidmeh? Is it a label or is it just a הלכה halacha
that it has to look like its mother? And if you want,
here’s how we could say what the debate is: ברחל בת עז
בת רחל, Berachel bas ez bas rachel, okay, which is whatever the
converse of Michael's case. Okay, the generations were sheep, goat, sheep. Okay,
and now מר סבר, mar savar, so what's the הלכה? halacha? On
the one hand, the child doesn't look like its mother, right? When
you go to the bottom, right, at the bottom of the thing
you have its sheep, goat, sheep. So at the bottom the sheep
is not like the mother goat. So that maybe is a נדמה.
nidmeh. On the other hand, maybe the problem of נדמה nidmeh is
not just a technical point that the child has to look like
the mother. Maybe the problem of נדמה nidmeh is that it has
to be the right species. So here, basically, the sheep gene is
reasserting itself and it is considered to be the right species. So
that's the debate. Okay, דמר סבר, de-mar savar, חזרה סייותא למקומן, chazra
seyusa limkoman, the sheepness goes back to its place. So it has
reasserted itself and therefore it is no longer a נדמה nidmeh because
now it's going back to its original sheep stock. ומר סבר, u-mar
savar, לא חזרה סייותא למקומן. lo chazra seyusa limkoman. No, sorry, it
still here is a child of a נדמה nidmeh and it, and
therefore even though, and therefore it remains either, either it remains a
נדמה nidmeh because if you would, the, what do you call it,
the, you know, genes have been tainted, or it remains a נדמה
nidmeh just because it doesn't look like its mother. So even though
it now goes back to its sheep identity, it still doesn't look
like its immediate mother. Now I have a better question, which was
if it's a goat, sheep, sheep? That would be the same as
the first question, which was oh, which was sheep, goat. Yeah, that
was, that was the first question. But what for? נדמה nidmeh is
just means looks like the other thing, doesn't look like the mother.
Okay, רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, let’s just get to the
דוחק, dochak, כגון שיש בו מקצת סימנים. kegon sheyeish bo miktzas simanim.
He has a much easier answer. He says in our משנה, Mishna,
our משנה Mishna said that even when the sheep doesn't look like,
even when a sheep gives something that looks like a goat, if
it looks a little bit like a sheep, it's still, it's still
obligated. So that's the case. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's
obligated. Why? Because it a little bit looks like the mother. And
how about the חכמים Chachamim who say you're exempt? ומאן חכמים, U-man
Chachamim, who are the חכמים Chachamim that say you're exempt? רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, דאמר עד שיהיה ראשו ורובו דומה לאמו, d'amar ad sheyehei
rosho verubo domeh l'immo, something we had earlier, which was רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says that a few characteristics like the mother is not
enough. It has to be the head and the majority like the
mother. So he says, ah, those are all very creative, but we're
talking about a simpler case. It looks somewhat like the mother, somewhat
not. Therefore רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you're חייב chayav and the
חכמים Chachamim who is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says a little bit
like the mother isn't enough, it has to look majority like the
mother. But why do we need a different debate about it? What?
Why do we need a different debate about it then? I don't
know, maybe it's just telling you that in one case it was
the חכמים Chachamim framed, it was always רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Sometimes we have that, that one time one is
framed as חכמים Chachamim and the other, you know, and it gets
reversed sometimes who is framed as the סתם stam position and who
is framed as the argument position. So we're going to keep on
discussing it. Okay, but that was certainly the more fascinating question, which
was about when the generation sort of alternated. And now the גמרא
Gemara is going to continue. So let's take a look. אמר רב
יוחנן, Amar Rav Yochanan, so said רב יוחנן, Rav Yochanan, מודה רבי
מאיר, modeh Rabbi Meir, so now we're going back to the more
creative ideas before, which is when it goes like goat, sheep, sheep,
or sheep, goat, sheep, that there's the question of how do you
define נדמה, nidmeh, right? If it's like its mother, but its, but
the mother itself was off, or like if it's like its grandmother,
but it's not like its mother. Okay, so is that a נדמה
nidmeh or not? And רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was basically saying you're
חייב. chayav. He was saying, yes, in those cases, however you define
them, I will no longer call it a נדמה nidmeh and I'll
say that it goes back to being a sheep or stays a
sheep or whatever. So now the גמרא Gemara is going to say
there are some cases that everybody agrees you need a pure line.
Okay, what are those cases? Let's take a look. אמר רב יוחנן,
Amar Rav Yochanan, מודה רבי מאיר modeh Rabbi Meir בשעיר של ראש
חודש, b'se'ir shel Rosh Chodesh, the goat of ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh,
רש״י Rashi says ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is לאו דווקא, lav davka,
it means the goat of, you know, that's brought for the מוספין,
Musafim, the goat of the חטאת, Chatas, דבעינן בן שעירה, d'ba'inan ben
se'ira, that it's not, that you need to be actually not only
a goat but born by a goat, and meaning you can't have
one of these cute goat-sheep-goat types of things going on. Why? מאי
טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? אמר קרא, Amar kra, the verse
says אחד, echad, right? ושעיר עזים אחד לחטאת, v'se'ir izim echad l'chatas,
one. So we're reading אחד, echad, המיוחד ובא מששת ימי בראשית, hamiyuchad
uva misheshes yemei bereishis, that basically it is a pure line going
back to the time of creation. So there is no time within
that line. Now again, what's fascinating about this is it's not really
about, you know, about other genes being mixed up. Because the גמרא
Gemara is not discussing that the father in any case, or a
mother somewhere in the middle, was a goat. All of them could
have been, meaning all of them could have been born by sheep,
or I'm sorry, we're talking about a goat. That the mother in
the middle somehow was a sheep, but the father somehow in the
middle was a ram. The only question is that the child looked
at one stage, right? Doesn't matter who the father is, at one
stage the child looked different. And that would be enough to say
that it somehow, you know, taints the line. So here we're saying
that when it comes to קרבנות, korbanos, you can't have a tainted
line, which doesn't just mean cross-species at one generation, but even means
one generation looked like the other species. Okay, now. Some type of
line forever is tainted going down. Yeah, that's what it says. That
it would be. Okay, I don't know how you'd prove it. You'd
ask the sheep to show their, like, their כתובה. kesubah. Exactly. Anyway,
okay. Again, what's always not clear about these things is what does
the גמרא Gemara think about נדמה? Nidmeh? Does the גמרא Gemara think
that it biologically is a sheep or like in this case it
is a goat, it just was a bizarre appearance and it looked
like the other species? Or does it actually think that no, sometimes
it can happen that a goat, a sheep can give birth to
a goat or a goat can give birth to a sheep? Okay,
obviously it makes more sense given this idea of the purity of
the line, you know, and those types of issues, or in the
case of sheep-goat-sheep-sheep, it makes more sense to think that the גמרא
Gemara thinks the thing really is the other מין, min, because if
it was just an appearance issue, why should it matter so much,
especially once it gets back to its original appearance? Okay, and you
have the whole question of what depends on what it looks like,
which is... I understand. Yeah, well that's true. Yeah, that's true too.
It sounds like the קובץ Kovetz because this is clearly nothing that
anybody ever saw. What? It's clearly completely theoretical. Yeah, you would think.
They don't acknowledge it. Right, right. I mean, clearly there was no
experience with such a... Right, I mean, you know, maybe there's sometimes
things that have somewhat some characteristics of other things. It's not like
a lion and a tiger. No, there are genuine times when you
can crossbreed. You can have crossbreed. That is true. Yeah, yeah, I
don't know. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this: והא מהכא נפקא
מהתם נפקא. Veha meheicha nafka mehatam nafka. One minute, I can tell
you that I know that a קרבן korban cannot appear like be
like a tainted line from another verse. It says שור או כשב
או עז כי יולד. Shor o chesev o ez ki yivaled. So
for an ox or, you know, it says an ox or a
sheep, then you bring it as a קרבן. korban. So we say
what are we learning out from the word ox or sheep? So
שור Shor is פרט לכלאים perat lekilayim to exclude a case of
a genuine mixed breed. או עז, O ez, a goat, פרט לנדמה.
perat lenidmeh. It excludes a case of even looking like the other
species. And of course the difference is that we're saying that it's
not even if this one looks different, but even if somewhere in
the line it looked different. So the גמרא Gemara says צריכא, tzericha,
you need both. ואי מהתם הוה אמינא הני מילי היכא דנחית לדרגא,
Ve-i mehatam hava amina hanei milei heicha denachit ledarga, like we just
said. If it were just that first, we would say fine, that's
when the animal itself looks different, not when we're talking about going
back generations. והיכא דנחית לנחית לדרגא, Veheicha denachit lenachit ledarga, but if
it's just a question about somewhere way back in the line, אימא
לא, eima lo, I would have thought it's not a problem. ואי
מהכא, Ve-i meheicha, if it was this verse, then הוה אמינא, hava
amina, I would have thought הני מילי, hanei milei, where it says
אחד מיוחד, echad meyuchad, it has to be a pure line. So
הני מילי לגבי קרבן חובה, hanei milei legabei korban chovah, maybe that's
true about like a חטאת, chatat, which is a communal obligatory קרבן
korban where we are very demanding. אבל נדבה, Aval nedavah, private free
will קרבן, korban, לא, lo, maybe it doesn't have to be a
pure line. צריכא, Tzericha, so we combine the two and we say
yes, you need it. Even by all קרבנות, korbanot, you need this
pure line and nowhere up the line could it have had an
animal that looked like a different species. You what? Question. Yes. Is
there any counterpart in the גמרא Gemara to חוששין לזרע האב chosheshin
lezera ha-av when it comes to human procreation, for example, in identifying
someone as Jewish or not Jewish? What do you mean? About whether
about whether like Jewish identity goes by the father? You know, you
can certainly, yeah, you can certainly imagine a lot more easily, you
know, different skin colors and so on. Right. But what do you
mean? חוששין לזרע האב, Chosheshin lezera ha-av, let's get... חוששין לזרע האב
Chosheshin lezera ha-av is do we recognize, is when we know who
the father is, the biological father is, but do we recognize that
person's relationship to the child? Now that is a question amongst animals
because they don't really have a family structure. It does come up,
I'm sorry to say but you're pushing me, in the context of
discussions relating to let's say, you know, slaves or non-Jews. How much
there do we sort of acknowledge the same sort of sense of
family structure and there as well. But again, the irony is of
course that yes, when it comes to religious, you know, identity, that
there we go by... well no, that actually is the point, that
you know, that we do go fundamentally by the mother. Right. So
what exactly then is your question? That about whether there's any... you
know, we all know it goes by the mother, but does the
גמרא Gemara ever consider the possibility that the father matters? Yeah, I'm
trying to remember. It sort of gets raised a little bit in...
I don't remember exactly to give you a precise answer. I'm trying
to remember whether it gets raised as a הוה אמינא, hava amina,
like as a total theoretical הוה אמינא, hava amina, or it actually
gets raised as a serious possibility. I mean it is there in
the conversation, but I don't remember the exact... I'd have to go
look at it again. Doesn't it go by the father in biblical
times? What? Well yes, the father is always about the tribe and
whatever, you know, and that's what, you know, the whole גמרא, Gemara,
that's sort of that's really the irony is that normally we say
like, you know, משפחת אב קרויה משפחה, mishpachat av keruya mishpacha, right,
that it's all, you know, the Torah is all patriarchal, it's all
based on the father-son relationship, you know, and here with the flip,
if you would, the more natural grouping is by mother-child, right, and
that's, you know, so yes, so that is the interesting sort of
contrast between those two. And that plays out here with the חוששין
לזרע האב. chosheshin lezera ha-av. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: Okay. Wait, so just our conclusion just at this point
was that קרבנות korbanos need a pure line, no matter what. Exactly.
Okay, הכל מודים Hakol modim that אין לוקין על צמר משום כלאים.
ein lokin al tzemmer mishum kilayim. Get this. If you had, now
presumably also this means not just that this particular animal doesn't look
like its mother, then you could say it's not really a pure
wool if this if it was a sheep born from a goat
or a goat from a sheep, it's not real wool. But now
we're saying no, no, even if somewhere way up in the line,
great-great-great-great-great-grandmother looked, was a goat or looked like a goat, then the
sheep then the sheep's wool here is not pure wool to be
חייב chayav for כלאים. kilayim. שנאמר Shene'emar as it says, לא תלבש
שעטנז Lo tilbash shatnez צמר ופשתים יחדיו tzemmer upishtim yachdav wool and
linen. מה פשתן שלא נשתנה, Ma pishtan shelo nishtanah, the same way
flax is always just flax, you never can have this type of
case. How, the גמרא Gemara why you can't I don't know, but
somehow you can, אף צמר שלא נשתנה af tzemmer shelo nishtanah must
mean wool that there was it was always sort of of a
line of pure wool, there was never anything in the middle that
interrupted. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, הכל מודים שצמר פסול לתכלת.
Hakol modim shetzemmer pasul letcheiles. You can't use that wool for תכלת
tcheiles of בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah or for ציצית, tzitzis, שנאמר, shene'emar,
לא תלבש שעטנז גדילים תעשה
לך.
lo tilbash shatnez
gedilim ta'aseh lach.
Don't wear שעטנז, shatnez, make for yourself ציצית. tzitzis. And by the
ציצית, tzitzis, of course, we
know that you have תכלת. tcheiles. So, and מה פשתן שלא נשתנה,
ma pishtan shelo nishtanah, the same way we just got through saying
that by the שעטנז, shatnez, which it is compared to the flax,
so that the same way flax is pure the wool has to
be pure, אף צמר שלא נשתנה, af tzemmer shelo nishtanah, the same
way wool has to be pure in order to be used for
תכלת. tcheiles. Okay, yes. Is there any scenario as far as we
know about cross-breeding vegetation? Well, right, so then it would say we're
not going to call it פשתן. pishtan. But of course how do
you know, meaning why doesn't it consider the possibility that you had
a cross-breed and then it or some, somehow the seed of something
flax looked different and then, why can't it imagine the same type
of a scenario? We're going to get that, we're going to get
to that possibility a little bit at the end. Let's keep on
going. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, okay, אף צמר שלא נשתנה.
af tzemmer shelo nishtanah. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak, הכל מודים שאין צמר מטמא בנגעים. Hakol modim she'ein tzemmer
mitamei benega'im. That if you make a garment out of it and
then it and then it gets a spot, it cannot become טמא
tamei from נגעים nega'im from quote unquote leprosy. שנאמר, Shene'emar, בבגד צמר
או בבגד פשתים. beveged tzemmer o beveged pishtim. This is something that
applies to clothes of wool or linen. מה פשתים שלא נשתנה, Ma
pishtim shelo nishtanah, the same way flax, linen does not have never
has this scenario, אף צמר שלא נשתנה. af tzemmer shelo nishtanah. פיין.
Fine. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, אף אנו נאמר, af anu
nomar, hey, let's get into the game. So therefore we can also
say, הדלה הגפן על גבי תאנה, hidla hagefen al gabi te'enah, let's
say you took a vine and wrapped it around a fig tree,
okay, and presumably that would impact the taste of the grapes, okay,
so make some type of a figgy tasting wine. So let's say
in that case, יינו פסול לנסכים,
yeino pasul lanesachim, you can't use the wine for נסכים nesachim on
the מזבח mizbe'ach for the wine part
that would accompany קרבנות korbanos on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. מאי טעמא, Mai
ta'ama, why? It says זבח ונסכים, zevach unesachim, because it compares the
two, a sacrifice and the wine. מה זבח שלא נשתנה, Ma zevach
shelo nishtanah, the same way we said the sacrifice had to be
of a pure line, אף נסכים שלא נשתנה. af nesachim shelo nishtanah.
So also the wine would have to be pure and here not
going to the question of previous generations, but at least not have
been in this sort
of scenario in which
the taste gets affected and tainted. מתקיף לה רבינא, Matkif lah Ravina,
so Ravina says one minute, הדלה פשתן על גבי היגה, hidla pishtan
al gabi higah, הכא נמי דלאו פשתן? hacha nami delav pishtan? So
what let's say I took my flax and this gets back to
that issue and
I sort of
intertwined it around, bent it around a thorn bush. So would you
also say that then it doesn't make something called it's not pure
linen and it doesn't qualify for all these things that you need
clothing for and linen for? So if so, אם כן, im kein,
if
that were true that you would say that when you do this
stuff with the
plant products, that it makes them considered changed and altered, if that's
true, לא מצינו מה פשתן שלא נשתנה, lo matzinu ma pishtan shelo
nishtanah, then how could we make our this basically what threw out
as we said before, oh, the same way flax never changes, these
other things never change. These other things have to be
pure the same way flax is pure. Who told you flax was
pure? Maybe you intertwined it with other types of things. So what
do you see? You see that by the plant products, as long
unless you actually create a crossbreed, right, and so this is basically
the answer. We're not talking about כלאים, kilayim, crossbreeds we know. But
unless
you actually create a crossbreed, there's no way to get with plant
products it to be considered to be changed. And therefore we could
say, since flax never changes, therefore, the wool has to be completely
pure.
So wrapping it around a tree isn't... that's what the גמרא Gemara
says.
But
that's his point. His point is you don't tell me that you're
going to פסול pasul wine because you can impact plant products. If
I would admit that plant products could have a similar scenario as
נצמת. nitzmet. as being tainted or impacted or changed, then I wouldn't
be able to have made all the previous דרשות drashos I just
made, because all of those assumed that flax will always be pure.
So what do you see? You see that unless you actually crossbreed,
whatever you try to do to manipulate plants does not really change
their identity. That's his argument. And the גמרא Gemara says maybe it
depends on the plant. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה
זה נשתנה ריחו וזה
לא נשתנה
ריחו.
Amar lei zeh nishtaneh reicho vezeh lo
nishtaneh reicho.
Big difference. Flax, you can't affect. What are you going to do,
flax? You could maybe create a crossbreed, but anything else you would
do is not going to impact the smell, the taste, the quality
of flax. So therefore flax always by its nature will be pure.
But if you actually, like
you know by the way, for example, this isn't exactly the same,
but you know when you go to the store and you buy
honey, you know they have clover honey and blueberry honey or whatever,
because it all matters like what are the flowers it's taking it
from. So here too, it says if the vine is wrapped around
a fig tree, it will affect the vine. So it's not a
categorical that plant products cannot be affected. Flax can't be affected. So
therefore we can make all our previous דרשה. drasha. So now we
are saying that, you know, it's very fascinating. A, we're introducing this
idea of נדמה, nidmeh, which is something which really is not as
we know biologically different, but somehow is considered different because it looks
different. And then we get these parallels about like, you know, affected
grapes for wine. And then you also though get the very interesting
idea that even if you go up multiple generations, right, you have
to have this purity of line even though really biologically it's all
the same, if at one stage it was looked different. Not for
normal purposes, but definitely for like מקדש Mikdash purposes and then for
other things as well, תכלת, tekhelet, בגדים, begadim, the whole list of
things in which you need this sort of purity of line. Weren't
we supposed to be bringing this בכור bechor as a קרבן korban
to begin with? And then so what was our whole debate? If
we had the דרשה drasha that by any קרבן korban it needs
to be like whatever it is, מן השעיר, min hase'ir, then there's
no question of this, right? You know that's a great point. Once
the גמרא Gemara concludes, once the גמרא Gemara concludes that it's not
limited to the to the שעיר se'ir or anything, even to a
even to a even to a קרבן ציבור חובה, korban tzibur chova,
so how could the גמרא Gemara have said before have said that
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir agrees to that if that was the whole
debate before about the בכור? bechor? That's a very, very good question.
I have to think about that. There's one or two possibilities. Either
he would say it's קדוש kadosh for a בכור bechor and it's
נקרא nikra and then
has to be eaten by a כהן kohen although, but the other
thing is is that, you know, is that the גמרא Gemara never
explicitly combined the two, meaning what it had for the קרבן korban
of the שעיר se'ir was even previous generations. What it had for
the נדבה nedava was when the animal itself is a נדמה. nidmeh.
The גמרא Gemara never explicitly, you
know, combined the two and said that even for a non, you
know, קרבן ציבור חובה, korban tzibur chova, it matters previous generations. It
implicitly was saying that, but never explicitly said that. That's a great
question. Let me see if I can get you an answer for
that. I'm sure that's addressed in the ראשונים. Rishonim. Okay, let's take
a look now at the next משנה, mishna, which is something that
we've seen before and gets us into a another fascinating conversation. רחל
שלא ביכרה וילדה שני זכרים. Rachel shelo bikra veyalda shnei zacharim. So
a sheep has never had children and gave birth to two male
twins. Again, that's like two weeks ago פרשה, parsha, two male kids,
although that was רבקה, Rivka, not רחל. Rachel. טוב טוב טוב. Tov
tov tov. Okay, two male twins at the same time. שני זכרים
ויצאו שני ראשיהם כאחד. Shnei zacharim veyatze'u shnei rasheihem ke'echad. And they
came out what looked like to be exactly simultaneous. So so what
do you do? Okay, which one is the בכור? bechor? So רבי
יוסי הגלילי אומר שניהם לכהן. Rabbi Yose HaGlili omer shneihem lacohen. The
כהן kohen gets both of them, שנאמר הזכרים להשם. shene'emar hazacharim l'Hashem.
It's possible to have two בכור bechor if they came out exactly
at the same time. If they were different times, of course, then
it would be different, but exactly at the same time they're both
בכור. bechor. חכמים אומרים, Chachamim omrim, and the חכמים Chachamim say, אי
אפשר לצמצם. iy efshar l'tzamtzem. No, you cannot be that precise. Even
though it looked to you the same time, we don't trust your
assessment that it was the same. We assume one was first and
the other was second and you just don't know. So what do
you do if it's a ספק safek which is which? So no,
well, well, here's the thing. So let's take though, the כהן kohen
definitely is entitled, you can't say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero
alav hara'aya, because the כהן's kohen entitled to a sheep. Okay, you
just don't know which sheep. Well, right, so that's what it's going
to be. So let's take a look. So it says אלא אחד
לו ואחד לכהן. ela echad lo ve'echad lacohen. The כהן kohen gets
one, you get you get the other. Now the question is which
is who gets what? רבי טרפון אומר הכהן בורר לו את היפה.
Rabbi Tarfon omer hacohen borer lo es hayafe. The כהן kohen gets
to pick the nicer one. Okay, why exactly? Unclear. Why don't we
say המוציא מחברו? hamotzi mechavero? רבי עקיבא אומר משמנים ביניהם. Rabbi Akiva
omer meshamnim beineihem. You estimate the difference of the two things, which
sounds like you basically give the כהן kohen the middle value of
the two. Of course, the middle value is neither sheep, so which
sheep do you give him? The גמרא Gemara assumes you give him
the cheaper sheep, right, and then you pay the difference. Okay, והשני
ירעה עד שיסתאב. vehasheni yireh ad sheyista'ev. Now, what do you have
to do? How do you eat them? You can't bring either sheep
as a קרבן, korban, right? Because either sheep, whether the one I
kept, the one the כהן kohen had, might be the wrong one,
and then you'd be bringing חולין לעזרה. chullin la'azar. And you know,
and you can't so you can't and you can't מקדיש makdish them.
You can't be מקדיש makdish בכור. bechor. So anyway, so what you
do is you have to wait for them to get a מום.
mum. . *Wait, "nekeivah".* נקבה. nekeivah. *Wait, "bechorah".* בכורה. bechorah. *Wait, "matanah".*
מתנה. matanah. *Wait, "Rabbi Yose poter".* רבי יוסי פוטר. Rabbi Yose poter.
*Wait, "Gemara".* גמרא. Gemara. *Wait, "Met echad mehem".* מת אחד מהם. Met
echad mehem. *Wait, "Rabbi Tarfon omer yachloku".* רבי טרפון אומר יחלוקו. Rabbi
Tarfon omer yachloku. *Wait, "Rabbi Akiva omer".* רבי עקיבא אומר. Rabbi Akiva
omer. *Wait, "Tosafot".* תוספות. Tosafot. *Wait, "Rabbi Yose HaGlili".* רבי יוסי הגלילי.
Rabbi Yose HaGlili. *Wait, "Rashi".* רש״י. Rashi. *Wait, "Mishnah".* משנה. Mishnah. *Wait,
"Korban".* קרבן. korban. *Wait, "Bechor".* בכור. bechor. *Wait, "Mum".* מום. mum. *Wait,
"Beis Hamikdash".* בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. *Wait, "Kohen".* כהן. Kohen. *Wait, "Mimah
nafshach".* ממה נפשך. mimah nafshach. *Wait, "Vechayav bematanot".* וחייב במתנות. Vechayav bematanot.
*Wait, "Amri dei bei Rabbi Yannai".* אמרי דבי רבי ינאי. Amri dei
bei Rabbi Yannai. *Wait, "iy efshar letzamtzem".* אי אפשר לצמצם. iy efshar
letzamtzem. *Wait, "efshar letzamtzem".* אפשר לצמצם. efshar letzamtzem. *Wait, "sham'inan lei".* שמעינן
ליה. sham'inan lei. *Wait, "de-amar".* דאמר. de-amar. *Wait, "de-Rabbi Yose HaGlili".* דרבי
יוסי הגלילי. de-Rabbi Yose HaGlili. *Wait, "Amri dei bei Rabbi Yannai".* אמרי
דבי רבי ינאי. Amri dei bei Rabbi Yannai. *Wait, "matanot".* מתנות. matanot.
*Wait, "chayav".* חייב. chayav. *Wait, "Tanna'im".* תנאים. Tanna'im. *Wait, "ein lakohen klum".*
אין לכהן כלום. ein lakohen klum. *Wait, "nekeivah".* נקבה. nekeivah. *Wait, "bechorah".*
בכורה. bechorah. *Wait, "matanah".* מתנה. matanah. *Wait, "Rabbi Yose poter".* רבי יוסי
פוטר. Rabbi Yose poter. *Wait, "Gemara".* גמרא. Gemara. *Wait, "Met echad mehem".*
מת אחד מהם. Met echad mehem. *Wait, "Rabbi Tarfon omer yachloku".* רבי
טרפון אומר יחלוקו. Rabbi Tarfon omer yachloku. *Wait, "Rabbi Akiva omer".* רבי
עקיבא אומר. Rabbi Akiva omer. *Wait, "Tosafot".* תוספות. Tosafot. *Wait, "Rabbi Yose
HaGlili".* רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabbi Yose HaGlili. *Wait, "Rashi".* רש״י. Rashi. *Wait,
"Mishnah".* משנה. Mishnah. *Wait, "Korban".* קרבן. korban. *Wait, "Bechor".* בכור. bechor. *Wait,
"Mum".* מום. mum. *Wait, "Beis Hamikdash".* בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. *Wait, "Kohen".*
כהן. Kohen. *Wait, "Mimah nafshach".* ממה נפשך. mimah nafshach. *Wait, "Vechayav bematanot".*
וחייב במתנות. Vechayav bematanot. *Wait, "Amri dei bei Rabbi Yannai".* אמרי דבי
רבי ינאי. Amri dei bei Rabbi Yannai. *Wait, "iy efshar letzamtzem".* אי
אפשר לצמצם. iy efshar letzamtzem. *Wait, "efshar letzamtzem".* אפשר לצמצם. efshar letzamtzem.
*Wait, "sham'inan lei".* שמעינן ליה. sham'inan lei. *Wait, "de-amar".* דאמר. de-amar. *Wait,
"de-Rabbi Yose HaGlili".* דרבי יוסי הגלילי. de-Rabbi Yose HaGlili. *Wait, "Amri dei
bei Rabbi Yannai".* אמרי דבי רבי ינאי. Amri dei bei Rabbi Yannai.
*Wait, "matanot".* מתנות. matanot. *Wait, "chayav".* חייב. chayav. *Wait, "Tanna'im".* תנאים. Tanna'im.
*Wait, "ein lakohen klum".* אין לכהן כלום. ein lakohen klum. *Wait, "nekeivah".*
נקבה. nekeivah. *Wait, "bechorah".* בכורה. bechorah. *Wait, "matanah".* מתנה. matanah. *Wait, "Rabbi
Yose poter".* רבי יוסי פוטר. Rabbi Yose poter. *Wait, "Gemara".* גמרא. Gemara.
*Wait, "Met echad mehem".* מת אחד מהם. Met echad mehem. *Wait, "Rabbi
Tarfon omer yachloku".* רבי טרפון אומר יחלוקו. Rabbi Tarfon omer yachloku. *Wait,
"Rabbi Akiva omer".* רבי עקיבא אומר. Rabbi Akiva omer. *Wait, "Tosafot".* תוספות.
Tosafot. *Wait, "Rabbi Yose HaGlili".* רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabbi Yose HaGlili. *Wait,
"Rashi".* רש״י. Rashi. *Wait, "Mishnah".* משנה. Mishnah. *Wait, "Korban".* קרבן. korban. *Wait,
"Bechor".* בכור. bechor. *Wait, "Mum".* מום. mum. *Wait, "Beis Hamikdash".* בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. *Wait, "Kohen".* כהן. Kohen. *Wait, "Mimah nafshach".* ממה נפשך. mimah
nafshach. *Wait, "Vechayav bematanot".* וחייב במתנות. Vechayav bematanot. *Wait, "Amri dei bei
Rabbi Yannai".* אמרי דבי רבי ינאי. Amri dei bei Rabbi Yannai. *Wait,
"iy efshar letzamtzem".* אי אפשר לצמצם. iy efshar letzamtzem. *Wait, "efshar letzamtzem".*
אפשר לצמצם. efshar letzamtzem. *Wait, "sham'inan lei".* שמעינן ליה. sham'inan lei. *Wait,
"de-amar".* דאמר. de-amar. *Wait, "de-Rabbi Yose HaGlili".* דרבי יוסי הגלילי. de-Rabbi Yose
HaGlili. *Wait, "Amri dei bei Rabbi Yannai".* אמרי דבי רבי ינאי. Amri
dei bei Rabbi Yannai. *Wait, "matanot".* מתנות. matanot. *Wait, "chayav".* חייב. chayav.
*Wait, "Tanna'im".* תנאים. Tanna'im. *Wait, "ein lakohen klum".* אין לכהן כלום. ein
lakohen klum. *Wait, "nekeivah".* נקבה. nekeivah. *Wait, "bechorah".* בכורה. bechorah. *Wait, "matanah".*
מתנה. matanah. *Wait, "Rabbi Yose poter".* רבי יוסי פוטר. Rabbi Yose poter.
*Wait, "Gemara".* גמרא. Gemara. *Wait, "Met echad mehem".* מת אחד מהם. Met
echad mehem. *Wait, "Rabbi Tarfon omer yach Can you be that precise,
or can you halachically assume that that is acceptable for defining it
as identical, as the same? So רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosei HaGlili
says yes and the rabbis say no. So he says אפשר לצמצם
בידי שמים efshar l'tzamtzem b'yedei shamayim even in a natural event, like
the birth of these twins. וכל שכן בידי אדם v'chol shekein b'yedei
adam certainly if it is human-made and manufactured. We'll talk about what
those cases are in a minute. ורבנן V'rabanan the rabbis say בידי
שמים אי אפשר לצמצם b'yedei shamayim ee efshar l'tzamtzem this natural event
of the twins, they would you cannot be precise, but that was
when it was natural. בידי אדם מאי? B'yedei adam mai? What if
it is a human case? Now, what do we mean by human?
There are two things going on here and this is sort of
a little bit of a debate רש"י Rashi תוספות Tosafot or whatever.
A, who constructs the scenario? Does the scenario happen naturally or did
you create the scenario? Okay you could imagine a case where you
created the scenario. Let's say the case about I don't know, the
גמרא Gemara talks about if you have exact amount of סכך schach
and sunlight or if you have a fence that's exact amount of
slat as open air. You've actually constructed the scenario and if you
construct a scenario which is exactly precise. The other case is forget
who constructed the scenario. The question is whether you had the time
and opportunity to measure. Right in the case that your sheep is
giving birth, you're just a casual observer, you're not taking out your
instruments to measure whether it's the same time or not as opposed
to other cases could be a natural event, but you actually are
able to go take out your yardstick and measure what's happening. Okay,
so you can understand in both ways בידי אדם b'yedei adam makes
it better to say yes, this let's say is precise. If you
actually worked to make it precise then maybe we'll admit that it
can be precise, or maybe even if you didn't work to make
it precise, but if you have the time to actually measure precisely,
then we'll admit that we'll consider it to be precise. So that's
what it says. The rabbis say when it was completely natural, it
was אי אפשר לצמצם. ee efshar l'tzamtzem. It looked like the same
time but we don't trust that, we assume it's different. Would they
say אפשר לצמצם efshar l'tzamtzem when it was more human constructed and
or measured? That's the question. The rabbis say nothing natural happens simultaneously
or it's just impossible to tell? That seems to be the point,
that it's impossible to tell, and therefore we don't concern ourselves with
that possibility. Now part of the question also here could be, which
is is that how halachically do we define and what's the degree
of precision we require for certain things halachically. Okay, but let's take
a look. Let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes with this. תא
שמע Ta shema come in here. חוט של סיקרא Chut shel sikra
חוגרו באמצע chogro b'emtza להבדיל בין דמים העליונים ובין דמים התחתונים. l'havdil
bein damim ha'elyonim uvein damim hatachtonim. The מזבח mizbeach in the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash had a red line in the middle to designate
the upper half and the lower half of the altar because some
קרבנות korbanot you sprinkle the blood on the upper half and some
you do it on the lower half. Okay, so you needed to
know where the half was, so they had a line in the
middle. Now one minute, it says ואי אמרת v'ee amrat אי אפשר
לצמצם בידי אדם ee efshar l'tzamtzem b'yedei adam if you say even
when it's done by human constructed and measured and so on you
cannot be precise, so what good is a line if you can't
trust it? So זימנין דקא יהיב עליונים למטה. zimnin d'ka yahiv elyonim
l'mata. Sometimes you'll do the blood that belongs above and you'll do
it right above the line but maybe the line is in the
wrong place and maybe that's really on the lower half. ותחתונים למעלה
V'tachtonim l'mala or you'll do the blood below but maybe the line
is too high and you've really done the below blood above. So
what good is a line if you can't trust it? So obviously
you can assume that the line is precise. Make it very thick.
דמרווח ליה פורתא. D'marvach lei porta. So you make it a little
thick. So therefore, right, total precision you can't have, but you make
it an inch thick and therefore any that degree that gives you
a buffer zone. Fine. תא שמע Ta shema come in here. ממידת
כלים ממידת מזבח. Mimiddat keilim mimiddat mizbeach. So how about the very
fact that the Torah says here's how you make the שולחן, shulchan,
two אמות amot this way and one אמה amah this way and
here's how you make the מנורה menorah and here's how you make
the מזבח. mizbeach. How could we ever think that we satisfied the
Torah's requirements? Maybe our measurements are imprecise. Okay. No, but that's what
the גמרא Gemara says the answer. Now in other times you could
say well what's the good of שיעורין shiurin in all of הלכה
halacha maybe you're imprecise? But there you could say the same thing.
Okay so you do a little bit extra, you do a buffer
zone. But you can't say buffer zone here because then if the
Torah says it has to be exact no more no less. Okay
so how could you say you've made the right vessel? So the
גמרא Gemara says שאני התם דרחמנא אמר עביד ובכל דמצי למיעבד ניחא
ליה. shani hatam d'rachmana amar avid uv'chol d'matzi l'me'avad nicha lei. Right,
the Torah says do it as best you can so do something
that as far as you can tell is this parameters and that'll
count you do the best you can. And then it throws in
a פסוק pasuk which רש"י Rashi just says doesn't belong here but
the גמרא Gemara does sometimes throw in when it's talking about the
biblical requirements of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. הכל בכתב מיד ה'
עלי השכיל. Hakol bichtav miyad Hashem alai hiskil. A פסוק pasuk by
דוד David which it was all revealed to me by God exactly
what it has to look like. Now what exactly that means in
this context, רש"י Rashi says that was a mistake, doesn't belong here,
but maybe it means like we can assume that God somehow to
say that God wanted to mean the way it can work for
you guys, do it the best you can. Anyways, that's the message.
Now of course what's important about that is is that that argument
then can be easily translated and this might be exactly. with Yosef
Grieby's point about אפשר לצמצם. Efshar Letzamtzem. Is it possible to ever
be 100 percent exact? No, you can't be 100 percent exact. Anyway
you could even argue that maybe in nature nothing happens as exactly
the same time, right? Always maybe one microsecond off or something like
that. But the question is what does הלכה halacha demand? So the
same way we're saying by making the כלים, kelim, you know sort
of do what to you looks right, you know do as close
as you can and that will count, that could be Rabbi Yose
HaGlili's basic point in general, right? I'm not saying it's exact from
a scientific perspective, but I'm saying if for you it's exact, that's
all הלכה halacha asks for, and that that's defined as the same.
That's the halachic definition of the same is that you did the
best you could. Okay, but here the גמרא Gemara sort of accepts
that point when it comes to the כלים kelim of the מזבח
mizbeach but says you might not be able to generalize that. That's
maybe a special case. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. So
אמר רב קטינא, Amar Rav Katina, תא שמע, ta shema, come and
hear. חלקה לשניים והן שוין, שניהם טמאין לפי שאי אפשר לצמצם. Chilko
lishnayim vehein shavin, shneihem tme'in lefi she'ee efshar letzamtzem. What's the evidence
that this is a special case with the כלים kelim of the
מזבח? mizbeach? Well, there is no evidence, but my point is that
this answer is so good that it should really require the גמרא
Gemara that if you make it a general... that's my point, that
this answer is basically the position of, you know, אפשר לצמצם, efshar
letzamtzem, which means I'm not saying you can scientifically be precise but
I'm saying what you do counts. Your ability, how you measure it,
that's what's going to count as the same. הכי השתא? Hachi hashta?
What? Sounds like a good proof. Sounds like a good proof. I
know, I think you have to say that I think here's the
point. Since the תורה Torah says do it, right, therefore, and we
are only human, clearly in you know sort of implicit in the
do it is do it the best you can. But when it
comes to other cases, the תורה Torah never said have two animals
born at the same time, the תורה Torah never said any of
these other things, so there maybe you could say that there the
law is play it safe. Here there's no play it safe, right?
Here there's basically, you know, here there's basically, you know, here there's
basically, you know, here there's basically, you know, do it, it has
to be precise. So it means what you do counts as precise,
but in other cases maybe the answer is play it safe. Okay,
but I agree that once you have set the precedent that, you
know, what you do counts, then why shouldn't that be applied across
the board? And that actually I think is Rabbi Yose HaGlili's point.
I'm not saying it's scientifically correct. I'm saying if for you it
looks the same then halachically it's the same. But right, but I
think the point here is that it would be impossible, the תורה
Torah here implicitly has to say it's good enough. But the question
is what other cases maybe we won't say good enough, maybe we'll
say play it safe. Let's take a look at one more example,
or this example. So here you have a case that חלקה לשניים,
chelko lishnayim, you have a pottery vessel that's broken in half. Now
when you break a pottery vessel as long as you don't have
the majority remaining it becomes טהור. tahor. Let's say you broke it
in two exact halves. והן שוין. vehein shavin. שניהם טמאין, shneihem tme'in,
they're both טמא tamei because you don't know that either one is
the minority, and that what you want to say, well neither is
a רוב, rov, but no, לפי שאי אפשר לצמצם, lefi she'ee efshar
letzamtzem, you can't be precise. Maybe one is the רוב rov and
to you it looks like half but it really is the רוב.
rov. And you might say they're exactly half, neither it's not the
רוב, rov, neither is a majority, so they're both טהור. tahor. No,
maybe it's a רוב rov and you can't be precise. So there
you see it's בידי אדם bidei adam and we're still saying you
can't be precise. אי אפשר לצמצם. Ee efshar letzamtzem. So אמר רב
כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, שאני כלי חרס דאית ביה גומות. Shani kli
cheres d'it bei gumot. Pottery, ever try to break a pottery in
half? You're going to measure that? It's got all the jagged edges.
Nobody thinks you can measure exactly by a broken pottery shard. But
that doesn't mean in other more easily measurable cases and when you're
controlling the scenario that we won't say that you can be precise.
So תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. נמצא מכוון בין שתי
עיירות. Nimtza mechuvvan bein shtei ayarot. You have a dead body and
you have to go to the nearest city to do the עגלה
ערופה egla arufa case. Let's say it's exactly between two cities. So
מביאות, שתיהן מביאות שתי עגלות, Mevi'ot, shteihen mevi'ot shtei agalot, דברי רבי
אליעזר. divrei Rabbi Eliezer. Both cities bring each one a calf. Now
מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Now if it was you assume that one
was definitely the close one, you just didn't know, weren't able to
precisely measure, you would just bring one calf and you would, you
know, and you'd sort of do like a condition, if you're the
close one then it's your calf and if you're the close one
then it's your calf. You wouldn't need two calves, right? You would
just stipulate if it was only one city. So why would you
bring two? מאי טעמא לאו משום דקסבר בידי אדם אפשר לצמצם? Mai
ta'ama? Lav mishum de'kasvar bidei adam efshar letzamtzem? It must be that
because it's human, what makes it human we'll talk about in a
minute, you can be precise, so we say actually both cities were
exact, equidistant, and therefore ובקרוב ואפילו קרובות, Uvakaroav ve'afilu krovot, and when
it says the close city it means even close cities, so it
is exact and therefore you bring two. So the גמרא Gemara says
לא רבי אליעזר סבר לה כרבי יוסי הגלילי דאמר אפשר לצמצם בידי
שמים וכל שכן בידי אדם. Lo Rabbi Eliezer savar lah keRabbi Yose
HaGlili d'amar efshar letzamtzem bidei shamayim vechol shekein bidei adam. Yes, that
is true that that's what's going on, that we're saying אפשר לצמצם,
efshar letzamtzem, but who said it's the חכמים? Chachamim? Maybe it's Rabbi
Yose HaGlili in our משנה Mishna who says אפשר לצמצם. efshar letzamtzem.
Our question was what's the חכמים. Chachamim. Now the only thing that
I want to end with is that this case about the dead
body that the גמרא Gemara is calling בידי אדם bidei adam is
very curious because well somebody did kill him but but he was
not put there for the purpose of being exactly equidistant. So this
pretty And therefore, and that's the question: If you had the time
to measure. That pretty much proves that the idea of בידי אדם,
b'yedei adam, it's sufficient not that you constructed the case, but sufficient
that you had the time to measure. And therefore, and that's the
question: If you had the time to measure, the חכמים Chachamim say
if you didn't have the time to measure, it just happened, we
can't trust what you observed, we'll assume it was different times and
it was not precise. But if you had the time to measure,
even if it happened naturally, there the question is maybe that we
will say the חכמים Chachamim will agree if when you measure it
comes out exact, that we assume that the exact means exact and
that we have to deal with them being exactly equidistant or exactly
the same time and so on. Or not. So we will pick
up with this tomorrow. You know in the Robin Hood case, where
he did split it exactly between the two? Oh right. But that
was for the romance, that's not for הלכה. halacha. That's a good
point.